Okay, בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*. All right, today's דף *daf* is ל"ח
*Lamed Chet*, thirty-eight, and we pick up
really at the bottom of ל"ז עמוד ב' *Lamed Zayin Amud Bet*.
We spent all of yesterday with a fascinating discussion comparing מצה matzah
*matzah* to חלה challah, *challah* because both for the מצוה mitzvah? *mitzvah*
of taking חלה challah *challah* there's the תורה's Torah *Torah's* use of
the word לחם lechem, *lechem* and מצה matzah *matzah* is לחם *lechem*.
So one of the qualities we've been focusing on is the fact
that מצה matzah. *matzah* is based on חמץ chametz. *chametz* and has
to have the quality to become חמץ chametz *chametz*. Also that it's
לחם עוני lechem oni? *lechem oni* and in some ways has to
remain plain. You can do fine flour and so on, but it
has to be plain for particularly you can't use other types of
fruit juices and oils, but other issues in which it cannot be
plain but it also is plain לחם *lechem*. And לחם *lechem* is
similar to that of חלה challah. *challah*, so a lot of the
discussion yesterday was around those comparisons around things like bagels and סופגניות
*sufganiyot*, etc., and whether those are considered לחם *lechem*. And as I
mentioned yesterday, a related question is what you make the ברכה *beracha*
on המוציא לחם מן הארץ *Hamotzi Lechem Min Haaretz*. Anyway, now we
turn back to some of the more obscure aspects about when the
מצה matzah *matzah* has different halachic statuses and how that might affect
it. You remember we had all these discussions about when it's ביכורים
bikkurim *Bikkurim*, when it's מעשר שני maaser sheni *Maaser Sheni*, and what
its status is. So we pick up with that again now. אמר
רב אסי *Amar Rav Assi*, two lines from the bottom on ל"ז
עמוד ב' *Lamed Zayin Amud Bet*, אמר רב אסי *Amar Rav Assi*,
עיסה של מעשר שני maaser sheni *issa shel Maaser Sheni* לדברי רבי
מאיר *le-divrei Rabbi Meir*,
פטור מן החלה *patur min hachallah*. Now you're going to be eating,
let's say you want to eat מעשר שני maaser sheni *Maaser Sheni*,
thank you. So again we are continuing with a comparison to חלה
challah, *challah*, but not as in the quality of bread, but in
this issue of its halachic status. So when we dealt with מצה
matzah *matzah* and eating מצה matzah *matzah* of מעשר שני maaser sheni
*Maaser Sheni*, the question was that it says בכל מושבותיכם *bechol moshvoteichem*.
Can you eat? You can only eat מעשר שני maaser sheni *Maaser
Sheni* in ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*. You can't eat it everywhere, and מצה
matzah. *matzah* says all of your dwelling places, so maybe that would
exclude מצה matzah *matzah* made out of מעשר שני maaser sheni *Maaser
Sheni*. Now we're dealing with other possible reasons to exclude certain things
that are מעשר שני maaser sheni *Maaser Sheni*. And let's take a
look. מעשר שני maaser sheni. *Maaser Sheni* לדברי רבי מאיר *le-divrei Rabbi
Meir*, if you have dough of מעשר שני maaser sheni *Maaser Sheni*
according to רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, פטור מן החלה *patur min hachallah*.
Where are we? Last line of ל"ז עמוד ב' *Lamed Zayin Amud
Bet*. You're פטור *patur* from חלה challah. *challah*. ודברי חכמים חייבת בחלה
*U-divrei Chachamim chayaves bachallah*, according to the חכמים *Chachamim* you're obligated in
חלה challah *challah*. Top of ל"ח עמוד א' *Lamed Chet Amud Aleph*.
Now why is that? חלה challah, *challah* doesn't have this idea of
בכל מושבותיכם *bechol moshvoteichem*, etc., so we're going to see. And who
is this רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* and who is this חכמים *Chachamim*?
So there's a classic debate of רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* and the
חכמים *Chachamim* whether מעשר שני maaser sheni *Maaser Sheni* is considered ממון
גבוה *mammon gavoah* or ממון בעלים *mammon baalim*. Who is the owner
of מעשר שני maaser sheni *Maaser Sheni* when you bring it in
ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim* and you eat it in ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim*? Because
if you think about other things that you eat in ירושלים Yerushalayim
*Yerushalayim*, must be eaten in ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*. What else other than
מעשר שני maaser sheni *Maaser Sheni* must be eaten in ירושלים Yerushalayim,
*Yerushalayim*?
Well, קדשים קלים *kodshim kalim* is in ירושלים Yerushalayim, *Yerushalayim*.
קדשים קלים *kodshim kalim*, שלמים shelamim, *shelamim*. So when you have a
קרבן korban. *korban*, you're eating it in ירושלים Yerushalayim? *Yerushalayim*, right? So
is קדשים קלים *kodshim kalim* considered ממון בעלים *mammon baalim* or not
ממון בעלים *mammon baalim*? Who owns the קרבן korban. *korban*? I mean
it's yours in the sense that you're entitled to eat it. It's
yours that you get the sort of the credit for having brought
it, but you know are you really considered the owner of it?
You're not allowed to sell it, you're not allowed to do anything
with it other than eat it. You have all these limits and
restrictions. So there's an opinion that maybe קדשים קלים *kodshim kalim* is
considered ממון בעלים *mammon baalim*, maybe it is considered yours because you
have those rights. Maybe it's considered ממון גבוה *mammon gavoah*. Technically it's
God's קרבן korban. *korban*, you know, it's sort of you get the
credit for it as it were, it has your name on it
that you're entitled to eat it, but ultimately what you're eating is
you're eating God's קרבן korban *korban* and it's not yours, it's God's.
So there's a similar debate by מעשר שני maaser sheni *Maaser Sheni*
that you have to eat in ירושלים Yerushalayim, *Yerushalayim*. Are you eating
God's produce in
ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*, right? And if you think about it also, nice
idea about מעשר *maaser* is you take this, you separate it and
you give it to God. But the way you give it to
God is you bring it to ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*, but you still
eat from it, but ultimately it is God's now food that you
are eating from. Or do you consider it to be no, it
is actually yours? Okay, so do the restrictions or the concept that
you can only eat in ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim* and you can only
use it in certain ways, or if you want to say differently
conceptually the fact that it's brought to God and brought in ירושלים
Yerushalayim, *Yerushalayim*, does that signify it as ממון גבוה *mammon gavoah* or
as ממון הדיוט *mammon hedyot*? Yours or God's? So this is a
famous debate between רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* and the חכמים *Chachamim*. And
what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying is that would determine, that
debate would impact whether you're obligated in חלה challah *challah* with the
assumption you only have to bring חלה challah *challah* from your dough.
If it's God's dough, you don't have to bring חלה challah *challah*
from it. So that's what רב אסי *Rav Assi* is saying, that
according to רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* you're פטור *patur* because it's considered
God's and according to the חכמים *Chachamim* you're חייב *chayav*. Top of
ל"ח עמוד א' *Lamed Chet Amud Aleph*. מצות matzos. של מעשר שני
maaser sheni *matzos shel maaser sheni*, מצות matzot *matzos* of מעשר שני
maaser sheni. *Maaser Sheni* even if you held that it was not
a problem of all of your dwelling places, you held like רבי
עקיבא Rebbe Akiva, *Rabbi Akiva* that in principle מעשר שני maaser sheni
*Maaser Sheni* could be. Because if it got טמא tamei *tamei* you
could redeem it, it could be eaten out of ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*,
in theory you could have מצה matzah. *matzah* of מעשר שני maaser
sheni. *maaser sheni*. But here there's another issue to contend with: this
issue of ownership. So לדברי רבי מאיר אין אדם יוצא בו ידי
חובתו בפסח *le-divrei Rabbi Meir ein adam yotzei bo yedei chovato be-Pesach*,
according to רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* that it's God's, not yours, it's
ממון גבוה *mamon gavoha*, you do not fulfill your obligation, it's not
your מצה matzah.
*matzah*. I'm sorry, where does it say it have to be your
מצה matzah.
*matzah*? Well, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will ask that. לדברי חכמים אדם
יוצא בו ידי חובתו בפסח *le-divrei Chachamim adam yotzei bo yedei chovato
be-Pesach*, according to the חכמים *Chachamim* you fulfill your obligation.
Similarly, אתרוג etrog של מעשר שני maaser sheni? *esrog shel maaser sheni*.
You have an אתרוג etrog, *esrog* of מעשר שני maaser sheni *maaser
sheni*, right? So it has to be an אתרוג *esrog*, right? Because
you would not have a לולב lulav, *lulav* or a הדס *hadas*
or an ערבה *aravah* because those aren't food, מעשר שני maaser sheni
*maaser sheni* is only out of food, so it can only be
your אתרוג *esrog*. So you've got אתרוג *esrog* of מעשר שני maaser
sheni. *maaser sheni*. לדברי רבי מאיר אדם יוצא בו ידי חובתו ביום
טוב *le-divrei Rabbi Meir adam yotzei bo yedei chovato be-Yom Tov*, according
to רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* you could fulfill your obligation. לדברי חכמים
*le-divrei Chachamim*—you cannot fulfill your obligation—אין אדם יוצא בו ידי חובתו ביום
טוב *ein adam yotzei bo yedei chovato be-Yom Tov*. לדברי חכמים אדם
יוצא בו ידי חובתו ביום טוב *le-divrei Chachamim adam yotzei bo yedei
chovato be-Yom Tov*, according to the חכמים *Chachamim* you can fulfill your
obligation on יום טוב *Yom Tov*. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is going to try to identify where we know that this idea
that they have to be yours. So מתיב לה רב פפא *masiv
lah Rav Pappa*, so רב פפא *Rav Pappa* asks on this claim.
בשלמא עיסה *bishlama isa*, I get the case of dough, of חלה
challah *challah*, that there's an issue of being considered yours, דכתיב *dechativ*
the verse says עריסותיכם *arisoteichem*, the first of your kneading troughs, possessive,
your kneading troughs, משלכם *mishalchem*, it has to be yours. אתרוג נמי
דכתיב *esrog nami dechativ*, an אתרוג *esrog* it says ולקחתם לכם *u-lekachtem
lachem*, yours, לכם משלכם *lachem mishalchem*, it has to be yours. By
the way, which is why it said אדם יוצא בו ידי חובתו
ביום טוב *adam yotzei bo yedei chovato be-Yom Tov*, right?
Because we know on the other days of סוכות *Succos*, not the
first days, you can borrow one, it doesn't have to be yours,
you only have to own it on the first day. So the
issue is using it on the first day when it has to
be yours. So I get that the חלה challah. *challah* and לולב
*lulav* and אתרוג *esrog* have to be yours, and if it isn't
considered yours, it's considered God's, it's a problem. But מצה matzah, *matzah*,
אלא מצה matzah *ela matzah*, when it comes to מצה matzah. *matzah*,
it asks Michael's questions: מי כתיב מצתכם *mi ketiv matzatechem*? It doesn't
anywhere say your מצה matzah, *matzah*. So who says? Let it be
God's, as long as you're not stealing it, as long as you
are allowed to eat it, who cares if technically it's considered to
be God's and not yours?
And what do the חכמים *Chachamim* say in terms of לכם *lachem*?
Because they say מעשר שני maaser sheni *maaser sheni* is considered לכם
*lachem*, it is yours. Meaning everybody agrees there's a requirement of לכם
*lachem*. There's a standing debate between רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* and the
חכמים *Chachamim* whether מעשר שני maaser sheni *maaser sheni* is considered ממון
גבוה *mamon gavoha* or ממון הדיוט *mamon hedyot*. So it says I
get that that's a problem if it's considered God's according to רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir* by חלה challah *challah* and לולב *lulav*, I don't
get why it's a problem by מצה matzah. *matzah*. So אמר רבא
Amar Rava *amar Rava* says רבא Rava *Rava*, ואיתימא רב יימר בר
שלמיא *ve-isayma Rav Yeimar bar Shalamya*, אתיא *atya* we may have a
גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* לחם לחם *lechem lechem*, is that it says
bread bread, like we spent most of yesterday comparing חלה challah *challah*
to מצה matzah *matzah*, although we did not use the גזירה שוה
*gezeirah shavah*, we just conceptually said it's a definition of bread. כתיב
הכא לחם עוני lechem oni *ketiv hacha lechem oni*, it says by
מצה matzah *matzah* poor person's bread, וכתיב התם והיה באכלכם מלחם הארץ
*u-khetiv hatam ve-hayah be-acholchem mi-lechem ha-aretz* when you eat from the bread
of the land you should separate out חלה challah *challah*. So therefore,
not only is the definition of bread the same like we talked
about yesterday, but even a technical requirement of owning it, if it
applies by חלה challah *challah*, it applies by מצה matzah *matzah*. מה
להלן משלכם *mah le-halan mishalchem*, the same way there it has to
be yours, אף כאן משלכם *af kan mishalchem*, here too it has
to be yours, which does raise an interesting question which the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* does not address but it addresses pretty consistently. So if
I go to
your סדר Seder *Seder* it's not my מצה matzah *matzah*?
Well, okay, but then you could say if I, you know, that
was a question we've had before, if I give you something, I
give you the right to eat it, to what degree actually, certainly
in the process of eating it is it considered yours? But I
would say that there's another question which, you know, is an issue
that comes up throughout מסכת סוכה sukkah *Masechet Succah*, the third פרק
*perek* that deals with the criteria that's absent here, which is the
question about מצה matzah. הגזולה *matzah ha-gezulah*. Are you, do you fulfill
your obligation with stolen מצה matzah *matzah*? You don't fulfill your obligation
with the stolen לולב *lulav* and אתרוג *esrog*. And what's missing also
from this פרק *perek* when we discuss the issue about like a
מצה matzah *matzah* of טבל *tevel* was the concern of מצוה mitzvah
הבאה בעבירה *mitzvah ha-ba'ah ba-aveirah*, doing a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* through or
intertwined with a sin, which is also very much of a concern
in the third פרק *perek* of סוכה sukkah *Succah*, which deals with
a stolen לולב *lulav* and other types of sin that you're doing
in the process of doing the מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*. So it is
interesting that it never raised directly in this פרק *perek* either the
issue of מצוה mitzvah, הבאה בעבירה *mitzvah ha-ba'ah ba-aveirah* or the question
of גזל *gezel*. But here it is saying this requirement of לחם
*lechem*. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is not done. So let's take
a look. לימא מסייע ליה *leima mesayei leih*, let me try to
give support to you, we have a ברייתא baraita: *braisa*. The ברייתא
baraita *braisa* says עיסה של מעשר שני maaser sheni money *isa shel
maaser sheni*, if you have dough made out of מעשר שני Ma'aser
Sheni *maaser sheni*, פטורה מן החלה *peturah min ha-challah* it's exempt from
חלה challah *challah*, דברי רבי מאיר *divrei Rabbi Meir* that's what רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir* says, וחכמים חייבת *ve-Chachamim chayaves* and the חכמים *Chachamim*
say it's obligated. So you see the standing debate of רבי מאיר
*Rabbi Meir* and the חכמים *Chachamim* about whether מעשר שני *maaser sheni*
is considered yours or God's would determine whether or not you're חייב
*chayav* in חלה challah *challah*. So that seems to be a proof.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says לימא מסייע *leima mesayei*? What do
you mean maybe it's a proof? היינו הך *hainu hach*, it's exactly
what you said! Look, they're debating this case of חלה challah *challah*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says yeah, but that's only חלה challah
*challah*, הכי קאמר *hacha ka'amar*, here's what he meant: לימא *leima* maybe
I could argue מדפליגי בעיסה *mi-de-palgi be-isa*... Since you see that they
have their debate by the dough, by the חלה challah *challah*, so
בהנך נמי פליגי *behanach nami pligi*, so presumably it would be a
similar debate by לולב *Lulav* and by אתרוג *Esrog* and by מצה
matzah *Matzah*. או דילמא O dilma *O deilma*, or maybe you would
say, now we already have a reason to know why מצה matzah
*Matzah* might be different because it's not clear you have to own
the מצה matzah *Matzah*, but maybe even אתרוג *Esrog* would be different.
Why would אתרוג *Esrog* be different? שני התם דכתיב עריסותיכם עריסותיכם תרי
זימני *Shani hasham dichsiv arisoseichem arisoseichem tray zimney*. Twice in the פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* it says the phrase עריסותיכם *arisoseichem* yours. So yours is
underscoring not just yours in the normal sense, yours and not somebody
else's and it's not stolen, etc., but even yours in the sort
of in the more technical sense, that even though you control it
and you're allowed to eat it, but if it's מעשר שני *Maaser
Sheini*, so in a theoretical way it's considered God's, even though practically
it's yours, but even that's enough to exclude it. So maybe the
exclusion of מעשר שני *Maaser Sheini* according to רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*
is only in the case of חלה challah *challah* where there's a
double demand of yours. But in cases like לולב *Lulav* and certainly
in cases of מצה matzah? *Matzah* where it doesn't say לכם *lachem*,
or לולב *Lulav* where it only says it once, maybe there even
רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* would allow מעשר שני *Maaser Sheini* to go.
Okay, so that's possible that they just because they argue by חלה
challah *challah* they don't argue elsewhere, but the argument of רב אסי
*Rav Assi* is that it applies in all cases, and the חידוש
*chiddush* for us is that by מצה matzah *Matzah* introducing this idea
of לכם *lachem* by מצה matzah. *Matzah*. Okay. Now, בעי רבי שמעון
בן לקיש
*Ba'ei Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish*. Now that we've discussed מעשר שני *Maaser
Sheini* and you might remember again what we said two days ago
that besides this issue of לכם *lachem* according to רבי מאיר *Rabbi
Meir*, מעשר שני *Maaser Sheini* is also an issue of the ability
to eat outside of ירושלים Yerushalayim, *Yerushalayim*, which we said the only
reason you the only way you would sort
of surmount that is according to רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*
since were it to become טמא tamei. *tamei* you could redeem it
and eat it out of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, that means that it's considered
theoretically eaten out of ירושלים *Yerushalayim* and therefore you can fulfill your
obligation with מעשר שני *Maaser Sheini*. Now we're going to have a
different variation on the מעשר שני *Maaser Sheini* question. Let's take a
look.
בעי רבי שמעון בן
לקיש *Ba'ei Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish*. רבי שמעון בן לקיש *Rabbi Shimon
ben Lakish* asked: מהו שיצא אדם ידי חובתו בחלה של מעשר שני
בירושלים *Mah she-yeitzei adam yedei chovaso be-challah shel Maaser
Sheini bi-Yerushalayim*? Okay. You can tell the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is having
fun. So you brought your מעשר שני *Maaser Sheini* to ירושלים *Yerushalayim*,
your dough, your flour,
you added water to it, you made it into dough, and then
you are מפריש חלה *mafrish challah*. Okay? And you give this חלה
*challah* to a כהן kohen *Kohen*. Or you're a כהן kohen *Kohen*,
but you give it to a כהן kohen *Kohen*. So here I
am, I have my dough of מעשר שני *Maaser Sheini*, I'm מפריש
חלה *mafrish challah* from it, I give it to Michael here who
for the sake of argument will be our resident כהן kohen *Kohen*.
He's going to eat this in ירושלים *Yerushalayim* as מעשר שני *Maaser
Sheini*, he's eating it in ירושלים *Yerushalayim* as חלה *challah*, he's eating
it as a כהן kohen *Kohen*. Fine. Now, can you be יוצא
*yotzei* with מצה matzah. *Matzah* made of מעשר שני *Maaser Sheini*? So
the answer is according to רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva. *Rabbi Akiva*, yes,
right? That's what we discussed two days ago. Can you be יוצא
*yotzei* with מצה matzah *Matzah* of חלה *challah*? Anybody remember? מצה matzah
*Matzah* made from חלה *challah* if you're a כהן *Kohen*? This was
in the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*. The answer is yes. Okay. So if
this were just חלה *challah*, Michael could be יוצא *yotzei* with it.
If it were just מעשר שני *Maaser Sheini*, Michael could be יוצא
*yotzei* with it. Now it is חלה *challah* of מעשר שני *Maaser
Sheini*. Why should that be any different? Let's take a look. Okay.
אליבא דרבי יוסי הגלילי
*Aliba de-Rabbi Yose HaGlili*, according to רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGelili,
*Rabbi Yose HaGlili* that argues with רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* and says
you can never use מעשר שני *Maaser Sheini*, לא תיבעי לך *lo
tiba'ei lach*, I don't have any question. השתא בחולין לא נפיק lo
nafik, *Hashata be-chullin lo nafik*, he doesn't allow you to fulfill your
obligation with unsanctified plain מעשר שני *Maaser Sheini*, בחלתו מיבעיא *be-challaso mibaya*,
certainly if it's also חלה *challah*, it's going to make it more
problematic. Okay. So obviously if you can't do it with מעשר שני
*Maaser Sheini*, the question doesn't begin. כי תיבעי לך ki tiba'ei lach
*Ki tiba'ei lach*, what's my question? אליבא דרבי עקיבא *Aliba de-Rabbi Akiva*
according to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* who says normal מעשר שני *Maaser
Sheini* you can fulfill your obligation of חלה *challah*. בחולין הוא דנפיק
*Be-chullin hu de-nafik*, that's normal non-חלה *challah* מעשר שני *Maaser Sheini*, plain
מעשר שני *Maaser Sheini*. Why? Then you fulfill your obligation. דאי מטמו
*De-im nitmeu*, what is the reason? Meaning the problem of מעשר שני
*Maaser Sheini* is that we've said that חלה *challah* has to be
able to be eaten anywhere and מעשר שני *Maaser Sheini* can only
be eaten in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. So what allows it to be considered
potentially eatable anywhere? Because we said דאי מטמו יש להן היתר במושבות
*de-im nitmeu yesh lahen heter be-moshavos*, because were it to become טמא
tamei *tamei*, this מעשר שני *Maaser Sheini*, you would be allowed to
redeem it and it would be able to be eaten, היתר במושבות
*heter be-moshavos*, allowed in מושבותיכם *moshvoseichem*, that's the word מושבות *moshavos*. Able
to be eaten anywhere. Able to be eaten in all places. So
normally the reason you could fulfill your obligation with מצה matzah *Matzah*
of מעשר שני *Maaser Sheini* is because you could in theory redeem
it were it to become טמא tamei. *tamei*. But now we've got
a problem because it's also חלה *challah*. What happens when חלה *challah*
becomes טמא tamei. *tamei*?
You're stuck. Right? חלה *challah* is like תרומה trumah. *Terumah*. תרומה trumah
טמאה *Terumah t'meiah* you have to burn it. You can't eat it.
So the whole scenario that would allow this to be eaten out
of ירושלים *Yerushalayim* from the מעשר שני *Maaser Sheini* perspective, that it
would become טמא *tamei*, would prevent it from being eaten because it's
also חלה *challah*. חלה. Okay? אבל חלה, Aval challah, now that it's
חלה, דאי מיטמי לית ליה היתר במושבות, de-i mitamei leis lei heter
be-moshavos, it would become טמא you cannot be eaten elsewhere, and it
can't be eaten anywhere. ובשריפה אזל, u-vsreifah azel, it would have to
be burned.
לא נפיק, so maybe you can't fulfill your obligation, okay? So חלה
you can fulfill your obligation, מעשר שני you can fulfill your obligation.
But when they come together, maybe not, because the scenario the argument
that works with מעשר שני is a scenario where it becomes טמא.
And that is a big problem if it's חלה. So maybe I'd
say you don't fulfill your obligation. או דילמא or maybe I should
say אמרינן amrinan we will say like this, הואיל ואילו לא קרא
עליה שם, hoy v-ilu lo kara aleha shem,
had you never made it into חלה, וקרא שם v-kara shem means
said the name over it, said this is חלה. Had you never
made it into חלה ואיתמיא אית ליה היתר במושבות v-itamya is lei
heter be-moshavos and had it never been חלה, had it just been
מעשר שני and become טמא you could eat it elsewhere. So ונפיק
v-nafik and you
fulfill
ונפיק בה v-nafik bah you fulfill your obligation. השתא נמי נפיק, Hasha
nami nafik, here too you fulfill your obligation. Now that's a very
nice type of a claim right it's like you know if grandma
had wheels she'd be a trolley car or something. If it weren't
חלה I'd fulfill my obligation. So now I should fulfill my obligation.
Okay but it is חלה right? How could you say oh well
you know so then say all the things that are problems you
know oh well had I never made it מעשר שני had I
never made it ביכורים had I never done this it would have
been okay. So even though now it is it's not okay. So
the way רש״י Rashi explains what entitles me to say oh had
it never been חלה is what the fact that really each status
by itself is acceptable. Calling it מעשר שני making it מעשר שני
doesn't make take it out of the מצה matzah category. Making it
חלה doesn't take it out of the מצה matzah category. Any one
of those statuses by themselves is not a problem with מצה. So
the fact that they happen to come together should not also exclude
it from the מצה category. That's the way רש״י Rashi explains it
but you can't just simply say had I never given it this
status it would be okay because the whole question deals with the
status that it actually does have. Anyway that's the גמרא's Gemara question.
When those statuses do come together does it become a problem or
not? So the גמרא Gemara, says like this: איכא דאמרי Ika damri
some say הא ודאי לא תיבעי לך. ha vadai lo tiba'ei lach.
That is goes without a question. That's obviously okay. דודאי אמרינן הוא.
d-vadei amrinan ho. We certainly can say this idea. It didn't have
to be חלה. And since it didn't have to be חלה and
since מעשר שני by itself is okay and חלה by itself is
okay when they're together that won't create a problem. Fine. That we
certainly say. כי תיבעי לך here's my question. If you weren't confused
enough here's my question. חלה הלקוח בכסף מעשר שני. challah halakuach b-kesef
maaser sheni.
Let's say you bought חלה with money of מעשר שני. What I
did was I didn't have grain, I had you
know whatever dates, okay, and I had a million dollars worth of
dates in my orchard which was out in you know somewhere in
Tel Aviv and I'm not going to schlep all that to ירושלים
so I redeem it all on a million dollars cash I'll make
it a thousand dollars and I bring my thousand dollars to ירושלים.
That's כסף מעשר שני. kesef maaser sheni. And what I do with
that money is I have to use food buy it for food
in ירושלים. When I'm in ירושלים I buy for food. I happen
to be a כהן so what I or whatever no a כהן
has חלה he was given חלה which is תרומה. I'm also a
כהן so I give him a thousand dollars because you know what
חלה and תרומה go at a discount right because it's limited who
can eat it so it's a you know so as long as
I'm a כהן I go ahead and I give a כהן a
thousand dollars I get tons of this חלה of מעשר שני חלה
and now it also has a מעשר שני status because I bought
it with my מעשר שני money. So it's the same idea of
the two together חלה and מעשר שני except it's מעשר שני because
I bought it with מעשר שני money not because it originally was
מעשר שני. Now why should that matter? It matters because there's a
debate about when something by מעשר שני when I need to I'm
allowed to redeem stuff that is original מעשר שני. What about stuff
that wasn't originally מעשר שני? It was purchased with מעשר שני money.
I went then I purchased חלה or apples or whatever I purchased
with מעשר שני money and now this stuff becomes טמא. Am I
allowed to redeem it? Maybe the תורה Torah only allows me to
redeem original מעשר שני. The logic the גמרא Gemara sometimes has says
is like this: the קדושה kedushah you know what was what was
the phrase from Star Wars Yoda the strong is force in in
this one right? So by original מעשר שני the קדושה kedushah is
strong in this one and if you have strong original קדושה kedushah
that somehow can exist independently and can connect to other things and
can be transferred out. Whereas if it is derivative קדושה kedushah it's
money bought with מעשר שני it's something bought with מעשר שני it's
very residual and somehow because it's weaker it's not strong enough to
go out of that and to transfer somewhere else. So that's the
debate can you redeem something that was bought with money. of מעשר
שני *Maaser Sheni*. Okay, so let's take a look. היא תיבעי לך
*hi tibei lach*, what's your question? חלה הלקוח בכסף מעשר שני *challah
halakuach bekesef Maaser Sheni*, חלה *challah* that is purchased with not original
מעשר שני *Maaser Sheni* but purchased with money of מעשר שני *Maaser
Sheni*. Okay. ואליבא דרבנן *ve'aliba d'rabbanan*, according to the Rabbis, there's a
debate of the Rabbis and רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* about what you
can do with this. לא תיבעי לך *lo tibei lach*, there's no
question. כיון דאמרי יפדה *keivan d'amri yipadeh*, the Rabbis say that you
can redeem objects that are bought with money of מעשר שני *Maaser
Sheni*. So היינו מעשר *hainu Maaser*, that's just like the original question
of original מעשר *Maaser* that was חלה *challah*. כי תיבעי לך *ki
tibei lach*, here's our question, אליבא דרבי יהודה *aliba d'Rabbi Yehuda*, according
to a position of רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, דאמר יקבר *d'amar yikaver*,
that says that if you bought stuff with מעשר שני *Maaser Sheni*
and then it became טמא *tamei*, you can't redeem it. It has
to be buried. It has קדושה kedusha, *kedusha*, you can't eat it,
you can't redeem it, bury it. דתנן *detnan*, where do you know
this debate? Because we taught in a משנה Mishna *Mishnah* in מעשר
שני *Maaser Sheni*. הלקוח בכסף מעשר שני *halakuach bekesef Maaser Sheni*, food
bought with מעשר שני *Maaser Sheni* money, שנטמא *she'nitma*, that became טמא
*tamei*, יפדה *yipadeh*, redeem it like original מעשר שני *Maaser Sheni*. רבי
יהודה אומר יקבר *Rabbi Yehuda omer yikaver*, רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says
bury it. Okay, so according to רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* that you
can't redeem it, now he's got an issue, okay? Because according to
him, forget that it was חלה *challah*. I should just סתם *stam*
ask if I buy מעשר *Maaser* with if I buy מצה *matzah*
with מעשר שני *Maaser Sheni money, can I fulfill my obligation? Remember,
what is the problem, the question about מעשר שני *Maaser Sheni* מצה
*matzah*? That you can't eat it out of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. So if
I buy simple מצה *matzah*, forget חלה *challah*, simple מצה *matzah* with
מעשר שני *Maaser Sheni* money, I can't eat it out of ירושלים
*Yerushalayim*. I can only eat it in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. And if it
became טמא *tamei* according to רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, I can't redeem
it. Okay, so I'm really stuck, and certainly now if you add
the fact that it's חלה *challah*, and then if it becomes טמא
*tamei* I have another reason I can't do anything with it because
as חלה *challah* I have to I also can't eat טמא חלה
*tamei challah*. So let's take a look. מאי *mai*? What?
Why would it not be allowed except in instances where it becomes
where what if they say it's okay unless it becomes טמא *tamei*
or
unless Because the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* taught two days ago based on
the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* that in all your dwelling places eat מצה
*matzah*, that it has to have the ability to be eaten anywhere.
And again, I pointed out at the time that's a little ironic
because the paradigm מצה *matzah* is the מצה *matzah* eaten with the
קרבן korban, פסח Pesach *Korban Pesach*, which is eaten only in ירושלים
*Yerushalayim*. But nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* understands that the independent מצוה
mitzvah, *mitzvah* of מצה *matzah* דוקא *davka* is independent and therefore has
to be able to be eaten anywhere. Okay, so what do you
say in this case? מאי *mai*? מי אמרינן *mi amrinan*, do we
say, הואיל ואילו לא לקיח הוה *hoeil ve'ilo lo lakuach hava*, since
were it not to have been purchased with מעשר שני *Maaser Sheni*
money, והואיל ולא קרא לה שם *vehoiel velo kara lah shem* and
had it never been חלה *challah*, ואיטמי *ve'itamei* and become טמא *tamei*,
יש לה היתר במושבות *yesh lah heter bemoshavot*, you could eat it
elsewhere, ונפיק בה *venafik beh*, fulfill your obligation, השתא נמי נפיק בה
*hashta nami nafik beh*, here too you'd fulfill your obligation. או דילמא
*o dilma*, or maybe, חד הואיל אמרינן *chad hoeil amrinan*, we say
maybe one what if hypothetical, ותרתי הואיל לא אמרינן *utrei hoeil lo
amrinan*, we don't say two hypothetically. Hypothetically this didn't have to be
חלה *challah*, and hypothetically this didn't have to be purchased with מעשר
שני *Maaser Sheni* money, and therefore if you had both of those
hypotheticals true, it would be okay, here too it's also okay. Now
again, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* and תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* say what is this
crazy statement that it didn't have to be חלה *challah* and it
didn't have to be whatever, right, it didn't have to be whatever,
anyway, right, it is,
I mean, you have to deal with its status. So again, רש"י
*Rashi* makes the argument he made before, which is that
both of those it didn't have to be is really a way
of saying the following. A: it didn't have to be חלה *challah*
is a way of saying that חלה *challah* status by itself doesn't
prevent you from doing the מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah* of מצה *matzah*, right,
that as an independent status there's no problem doing the מצוה mitzvah,
*mitzvah* of מצה *matzah* with חלה *challah*. Okay? It's only because it
comes together with מעשר שני *Maaser Sheni*, but independently it doesn't. So
maybe we could bracket the חלה *challah* status because by itself it's
not a problem. How about the fact that it's purchased with מעשר
שני *Maaser Sheni* money? That prevents it from being eaten elsewhere. Yes,
but ultimately that's a status that's derivative of the מעשר שני *Maaser
Sheni* status, and had it had the original מעשר שני *Maaser Sheni*
status it wouldn't be a problem. So is it right now a
problem? Yes, it is a problem right now. But the חלה *challah*
thing which is creating a problem is by itself okay, so maybe
we don't have to look at the intersection, we just say as
חלה *challah* it's okay, even though as מעשר שני *Maaser Sheni* it's
not okay, that's only because it's derivative מעשר שני *Maaser Sheni*. If
it were original מעשר שני *Maaser Sheni*, it would be okay. So
maybe the fact that it's derivative status makes the problem, that we
can bracket. That's how רש"י *Rashi* understands the הואיל *hoeil* arguments. Can
you make both of those statements or not? So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, ואמר רבא Rava, מסתברא *ve'amar Rava mistavra*, it makes sense,
שם מעשר חד הוא *shem maaser chad hu*, it's all מעשר שני
*Maaser Sheni*, and since as מעשר שני *Maaser Sheni* it's okay, then
even as derivative
מעשר שני *Maaser Sheni* it's okay. All right, so here the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is having some fun about playing with these ideas, right?
What's the status of מצה *matzah* of מעשר שני *Maaser Sheni*? So
one issue is can it be eaten out of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, that
was a debate of רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* and רבי יוסי הגלילי
Rebbe Yose HaGlili, *Rabbi Yose HaGalili*. One issue is is it considered
yours, and do you have a concept, a requirement of yours? מצה
and then the third idea is, oh what if we put these
two categories together? חלה is okay and מעשר שני is okay, what
if they you had both? Would that create problems or not? And
then in the end the גמרא Gemara is inclined to say since
independently they're okay, then even together they're okay. All right, one last
case of these funny statuses of מצה and can you do it.
And that's the last case in the משנה Mishna of חלות תודה
רקיקי נזיר. chalos Todah rekikei Nazir. I'll remind you what the משנה
says. It says if you make the bread for a תודה, Todah,
right, a now again, by the way, what's one part of davening
we don't say over all of פסח Pesach. in the פסוקי דזמרא?
Pesukei D'Zimra? We don't say מזמור לתודה. Mizmor L'Todah. Why don't we?
Because that stands for the קרבן תודה, Korban Todah, and the קרבן
תודה Korban Todah comes with forty loaves of bread, ten of which
are חמץ. chametz So you can't bring the תודה Todah on פסח.
Pesach. You can however bring a תודה Todah on ערב פסח, Erev
Pesach, but actually maybe not because you then you limit the time
you can eat the bread because you can't eat the bread all
the way you normally would be able to eat the bread the
whole day, you bring it ערב פסח Erev Pesach you can't. Anyway,
that's why we don't say מזמור לתודה Mizmor L'Todah even on ערב
פסח. Erev Pesach. Go check your סידור. siddur. So, okay, but you
now went ahead and you made not the חמץ chametz. part of,
not oh really, not the חמץ chametz, part of the תודה Todah
bread, but the מצה part, thirty loaves are מצה. Or you made
מצה types of bread that's going to be used as a for
like wafers that are used that the תורה Torah says you bring
for a נזיר Nazir who brings his קרבן. korban Okay, now these
are all מצה. Can you do eat them on סדר Seder night
and do your מצוה? mitzvah. All right, now what is going to
become clear in the גמרא Gemara or the גמרא Gemara isn't clear
but רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot are clear about it is we
don't actually mean that you brought your קרבן. korban Okay, because what
we mean is you made it for that purpose but you have
not yet sanctified it. And even so, the משנה says the following:
if you made it for yourself, you can't use them for the
מצוה mitzvah, of מצה. If you made it to sell in the
marketplace because you knew people were wanted to bring a קרבן תודה
Korban Todah or נזיר Nazir and you were going to sell it
to potential buyers, you were one of those people who owned those
shops, you know, right right by the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, you
know that you know we've uncovered the whole, you know, portico or
whatever, and you had a special shop to sell people their חלות
תודה ורקיקי נזיר chalos Todah v'rekikei Nazir and you made it to
sell, then you can use it for the סדר seder night. Now
again, the very fact that we talk about you using it for
yourself as opposed to, you know, and you made it to sell
shows you didn't sanctify it. Once you sanctify it for somebody else,
you know, at, you know, that scenario making it for somebody else,
you're not sanctifying it, the person who's going to buy it is
going to sanctify it.
So let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara says. מנא הני
מילי? Mena hanei mili? Where does this come from, this type of
a distinction? אמר רבא Amar Rava or or actually that the distinction
the גמרא Gemara will get to at the end. What's the problem
of using this? So אמר רבא Rava. דאמר קרא, da'amar kra, the
פסוק pasuk says, ושמרתם את המצות, Ushmartem et hamatzos, you should watch,
guard the מצות. matzot מצה המשתמרת לשם מצה, Matzah hamishtameres leshem matzah,
it has to be watched for the purpose of the מצה. יצא
זו, Yatza zo, to to exclude these cases, שאין משתמרת לשם מצה,
she'ein mishtameres leshem matzah, you don't watch it for the purpose of
מצה, אלא לשם זבח, ela leshem zevach, you're focusing on it to
bring it as a קרבן. korban, But you're still watching it that
it doesn't become חמץ. chametz. Right, now you're still watching it, Michael
says correctly, since the קרבן korban requires that these be מצה and
not חמץ, chametz, you still are watching that it doesn't become חמץ.
chametz. So if you look at רש״י, Rashi, so what's the problem?
You are protecting it from being you know you're making sure it's
מצה. So if you look at the top רש״י Rashi in ל״ח
ע״ב, lamed-chet amud-bet, רש״י Rashi says ושמרתם את המצות, Ushmartem et hamatzos,
עבדי ליה שימור לשם מצה. avdei leh shimur leshem matzah. רש״י Rashi
says כל שימור שאתה משמרה, kol shimur she'ata mishamrah, any guarding that
you do, שלא תחמיץ, shelo tachmitz, that you're the guarding is for
this purpose, to make sure it does not ferment, to become חמץ,
chametz,
התכוון לשם מצה של מצוה. hitkaven leshem matzah shel mitzvah. It has
to be not just to protect it from fermenting, but it has
to be לשמה. lishmah. It has to be for the purpose of
it being
מצת מצוה. matzas mitzvah. You know and that you need to do
it for the sake of being used as מצוה מצה mitzvah matzah
and not just making sure it doesn't become חמץ. chametz So this
גמרא Gemara is a good basis to say you need more than
just preventing חמץ, chametz. because it says if you're watching it and
you are watching it to prevent that it becomes חמץ chametz, because,
you know, as for to use for a תודה Todah or נזיר,
Nazir, it has to be מצה, not חמץ. chametz It's still not
good because it wasn't done for the explicitly for the sake of
the מצוה mitzvah. of מצה. It was done for a different purpose
and therefore it's a problem.
But still why are you choosing to read it this way? Because
you know the תורה Torah, is so מקפיד makpid and לא יראה
חמץ ולא יראה שאור, lo yeira'eh chametz v'lo yeira'eh se'or, why can't
you just read it in the same way that
it's all been I understand, I don't know, I mean חז״ל Chazal
have different דרשות, drashos, okay, not everybody's going to agree with this,
but let's take a look. Okay, but this requires this requirement that
it not just be not חמץ, that it be done for מצוה
purposes and this wasn't done for מצה מצוה. matzah mitzvah.
Yes, why don't you want an אתרוג when it's growing?
Well, it doesn't have a פסוק pasuk. ושמרתם. ushmartem. Okay? Here you
have a פסוק pasuk ושמרתם את המצות. ushmartem et hamatzot. But it
is true that, if your point is, that other מצוות mitzvot don't
have a לשמה lishmah requirement, you are correct about that. Meaning, you
know, there are issues that come up like what we mostly find
the לשמה lishmah requirement is by like objects of
קדושה, right? תפילין, tefillin, מזוזות, mezuzot, ספר תורה, sefer Torah, מצווה mitzvah
objects we don't find the לשמה lishmah requirement. A perfect example is
like you say לולב, אתרוג, a סוכה sukkah. can be all a
סוכה has to be made is for the purpose of shade. It
does not have to be made for the purpose of the מצווה,
mitzvah, okay? It doesn't even have to be made by a Jew,
okay, for a סוכה. So here it is a unique, not a
general requirement of מצווה mitzvah objects, but specifically by מצה and learned
from this פסוק. pasuk Now why do you learn read the פסוק
pasuk that way? That's Michael's question, but at least you have a
פסוק pasuk that is the basis for it. But let's keep on
reading. Not everybody agrees to this. רב יוסף אמר, Rav Yosef amar,
רב יוסף Rav Yosef says, אמר קרא amar kra the פסוק says,
שבעת ימים מצות תאכלו. shivat yamim matzot tochelu. You have to eat
מצה seven days, like the פסוק eat מצה in all of your
dwelling places. So the same way dwelling places we learn a criterion
that it has to be able to be eaten in your dwelling
places, here too we learn a criterion it has to be able
to be eaten for seven days. מצה נאכלת לשבעה ימים, matzah nechelet
leshiva yamim, מצה that's eaten for seven days. יצא זו שאינה נאכלת
לשבעה ימים אלא יום ולילה yatza zo she'enah nechelet leshiva yamim ela
yom valaila
to exclude this because תודה, todah, the bread of the תודה todah
or of the נזיר nazir can only be eaten for one day,
afterwards it becomes נותר, notar, right, leftover, as a part because it
becomes part of the קרבן, korban. and therefore it's not able to
be eaten for all seven days. Now רש"י and תוספות Tosafot both
point out, and they're forced to say this based on the later
גמרא, Gemara because of the idea of selling it in the marketplace
that you haven't sanctified it yet. So if you haven't sanctified it
yet, so it can be eaten for seven days, it's not yet
sanctified. So what they wind up saying is it means it has
to be the it goes back on the idea of ושמרתם את
המצות. ushmartem et hamatzot. It has to be made for the purpose
of being able to be eaten for seven days. And something that
is made with the intent that you could would only be able
to be eaten on one day, I mean it's true if you're
paying whatever you pay $20 a pound for שמורה מצה, shmura matzah,
it's because you're eating it on the סדר night, not because you're
eating it the rest of פסח. Pesach But at least when you're
making it you're not in your mind saying like it's not going
to be able to be eaten the rest of the time. Whereas
these if they're made with the intent of not being able to
be eaten for more than one day, then you've got a problem.
Okay so that's it. And according to that, it would not need
the requirement to be done for the sake of מצה מצווה, matzah
mitzvah, right? This is an issue actually an important larger debate of
do you need something for the sake of מצה מצווה. matzah mitzvah.
According to the second approach you don't. It's only a problem because
you specifically were doing it for a one day purpose. But if
you didn't have that negative intent, you would not need it to
be done for the sake of מצה מצווה. matzah mitzvah. Yes?
According to the first interpretation, if I say you know what I
know I'm going to have to go to ירושלים and I know
you know you
might wind up eating it for מצה. So we'll see that, that'll
be the scenario in the end. Hold on. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: תניא כוותיה דרבא ותניא כוותיה דרב יוסף. tanya
kevatei de'Rava vetanya kevatei de'Rav Yosef. We learned like רבא we learned
like רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. תניא כוותיה דרבא, tanya kevatei de'Rava, we
learned like רבא, here's a ברייתא: יכול יצא אדם ידי חובתו בחלות
תודה ורקיקי נזיר? yachol yetze adam yedei chovato bechalot todah verkikei nazir?
Maybe you could fulfill your מצה obligation with these, you know, מצות
of a תודה todah and of a נזיר. nazir. תלמוד לומר Talmud
lomar ושמרתם את המצות, ushmartem et hamatzot, מצה המשתמרת לשם מצה, matzah
hamishtameret leshem matzah, it has to be watched for the purpose of
the מצה מצווה. matzah mitzvah. יצא זו שאינה משתמרת לשם מצה אלא
לשם זבח, yatza zo she'enah mishtameret leshem matzah ela leshem zevach,
this is watched for the קרבן korban, purpose not for the מצה
purpose. That's like רבא. תניא
כוותיה דרב יוסף, tanya kevatei de'Rav Yosef, and we have a ברייתא
like רב יוסף Rav Yosef which says the exact same thing he
said. יכול יצא אדם ידי חובתו בחלות תודה ורקיקי נזיר? yachol yetze
adam yedei chovato bechalot todah verkikei nazir? Maybe you'd fulfill your obligation
with these מצות of these קרבנות. korbanot. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar the
verse teaches, שבעת ימים
מצות תאכלו, shivat yamim matzot tochelu,
eat מצה for seven days. מצה נאכלת לשבעה, matzah nechelet leshiva, מצה
that can be eaten for seven, יצא זו yatza zo to exclude
this שאינה נאכלת לשבעה she'enah nechelet leshiva that again was not made
was made without the ability to be eaten for seven, even though
it hasn't been sanctified yet. אלא יום ולילה, ela yom valaila, only
for a day and the following night. Okay so now the גמרא
Gemara says fine. So I get these new reasons you've given, what
purpose was it made for, for מצה purpose, for קרבן korban purpose,
one day seven days. But the גמרא Gemara says there's a better
reason why this stuff should not be you can't fulfill your obligation.
ותיפוק ליה, vetepok lei, how about say the reason you can't do
your מצווה mitzvah is מלחם עוני, melechem oni, poor person's bread. משנאכל
באנינות, mishene'echal ba'aninut, it has to be able to be eaten remember
the דרשה drasha we said before, at least according to רבי יוסי
הגלילי, it has to be able to be eaten even if somebody
is an אונן, onen, even if somebody has just suffered an immediate
death in the family. Right, this idea of affliction and אונן onen
and אנינות. aninut. יצא זו שאינה נאכלת באנינות אלא בשמחה, yatza zo
she'enah ne'echal ba'aninut ela besimcha, this cannot be eaten in אנינות aninut
it has to be eaten in שמחה, simcha, like you know all
קרבנות korbanot you can't eat when a person can't eat when they're
an אונן. onen. So therefore and this is connected to a קרבן,
korban so that's the reason it should be excluded. Who needs these
other new reasons? So the גמרא Gemara says, סבר לה כרבי עקיבא.
sava lah k'Rebbe Akiva. No, he, the author of this, these תנאים
Tanaim hold like רבי עקיבא, not like רבי יוסי הגלילי, and רבי
עקיבא feels it doesn't need this idea of being able to be
eaten by an אונן. onen. דאמר עני כתיב, D'amar ani ksiv, he
says you read it עני ani and not עוני, oni, and he
rejects this idea that it's only good if it could be eaten
in theory by an אונן. onen.
So the גמרא Gemara says, alright, ותיפוק ליה, v'teipok lei, the גמרא
Gemara says, how about, I have another reason why. Now again, notice,
I re-underscore this point, it's not yet sanctified.
So, you know, the גמרא Gemara. says, well, why don't we say
it can't be eaten באנינות? b'aninut? But you know what? It's not
sanctified now. So all of these issues the גמרא's bringing up is
that these criteria should exclude it because of the purpose for which
it's made. Even if it's not yet sanctified and doesn't yet have
that status, since it's made for that purpose, that should be excluding
it. So one thing we wanted to exclude it was this issue
of אנינות aninut and we said we're going according to רבי עקיבא.
So the גמרא says, ותיפוק ליה דהוי מצה עשירה. v'teipok lei d'havei
matzah ashirah. How about the fact that it is rich מצה? Why
is it rich? Because what you do with these loaves, both by
the תודה toda and the נזיר nazir is you pour oil on
them. And if it's got oil added to it, that makes it
מצה עשירה. matzah ashirah. So, and that is not just a question
of your intent. If you actually made it, you've actually, you know,
put the oil on it. So, why isn't that an issue? Okay,
so let's see what the גמרא says.
דהוי ליה מצה עשירה, D'havei lei matzah ashirah, that's the reason to
exclude it. So אמר שמואל בר רב יצחק, Amar Shmuel bar Rav
Yitzchak, רביעית היא. revi'is hi. No, 'cause you only use a רביעית
revi'is of oil. What's a רביעית? revi'is? It's about three and a
half ounces, okay? That's the amount of oil you use, and ומתחלקת
היא לכמה חלות, umis'chalekas hi l'kama chalos, and you divide it to
20 loaves of bread. So it's this much oil for, you know,
that much bread, that's not enough to make it לחם עשירה. lechem
ashirah. You know, so what is, right, so the question is, so
Micah of course says, so what's the limit? How much additives can
you add and it still be לחם עוני? So the גמרא never
gives it an exact amount, but certainly says this won't be the
problem. Okay, so that's one. Now I want you to be clear
that the reason the גמרא doesn't look for an easier reason to
exclude it, like this idea of אנינות aninut or עשירה, ashirah, is
'cause those reasons would not necessarily sufficiently explain the difference we're working
up to of whether you made it for yourself or you made
it to sell in the marketplace, right? If the problem was, was
that it was לחם, not לחם עוני because it was, it had
oil in it, then who cares if you made it for the
marketplace, it has the same problem. Okay, so we have to come
up with a reason that excludes it, but somehow is going to
allow for this difference of whether you made it for yourself or
you made it for sale. Okay, so it's not that it can't
be eaten באנינות, b'aninut, it's not that it has oil, those are
not the reasons. But the גמרא has another issue. The גמרא says,
ותיפוק ליה, v'teipok lei, why not learn it out,
ותיפוק ליה דאינו נאכלת בכל מושבות. v'teipok lei d'eino ne'echalas b'chol moshavos.
Now, if again, it's not yet sanctified, but were it to be
sanctified, it would be part of the קרבן korban and you can't
eat it out of ירושלים, right? So, remember we just got through
discussing that. Something that can't be eaten out of ירושלים, you're not,
isn't good. And you can't say, were it to become טמא. You
can't redeem it, it's part of a קרבן. korban So why isn't
that enough to exclude it, that it can't be eaten out of
ירושלים? So אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, so ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish says, זאת אומרת, zos omeres, from the fact that we had
to look for other reasons and we didn't say it was excluded
because it had to be eaten only in ירושלים, this teaches you
that חלות תודה רקיקי נזיר, chalos toda r'kikei nazir, the bread of
the תודה toda and the wafers of a
נזיר, nazir, נאכלים בנוב וגבעון, ne'echalim b'Nov v'Givon, can be eaten in
נוב Nov and גבעון. Givon. What does that mean?
So, when the בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael entered in to ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, which is what we're building up to now in the
reading of the תורה, right, they entered into ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
they spent 14 years conquering and dividing the land. During that period,
there was, you know, you had במות, bamos, you had, you know,
private altars. You didn't have a central location. Then they had, they
came to שילה Shilo and they built a ten, you know, they
established the משכן Mishkan there. No. נוב וגבעון Nov v'Givon were later.
They came to שילה, Shilo, they established the משכן Mishkan there, and
that functioned pretty similar to the way ירושלים would function in the
future, which is is that you could only bring in שילה Shilo
and anything could be eaten sort of, it had to be eaten
the קרבנות, korbanot, like the שלמים, Shlomin whatever, had to be eaten
in the environs of שילה. Shilo. Then you had, then שילה Shilo
was destroyed and you went back to a period where private altars
were permissible. Then they actually, and you might remember that there was
a whole story about, you know, about the ארון aron being taken
captive and so on, so and then when they reclaimed the ארון,
aron, they put it somewhere else and then the sort of central
place was of of worship, but it was not central to the
degree like שילה Shilo was. Anyway, but the quasi-central place of worship
was נוב עיר כהנים, Nov Ir Kohanim, because then דוד David comes
and דוד, David, if you remember, is running away from שאול Shaul
and he goes to נוב Nov and then שאול Shaul wipes out
נוב Nov and so on. So that's where it was. Now when
things were in נוב Nov and then afterwards it went from נוב
Nov to גבעון. Givon. When they were there, it was sort of
like did not have that full status like שילה. Shilo. שילה Shilo
had and therefore, even though it was the central altar, okay, and
therefore during that period, even if you were to bring a קרבן,
korban right, in, I mean, you still had private קרבנות korbanot and
private altars, right? What's the story by שאול Shaul and דוד David
and יהונתן, Yehonatan, where he says where's דוד, David, right? And he
says, you know, he's going back, he has a private, right, he
has a קרבן korban for his family and so on. Anyway, but
you did at least have, so it wasn't exclusive the way שילה
Shilo was, but you did at least have a central public altar.
And in that central public altar, okay, but it did not have
like a status of like the city, the, the place where you
brought had a status, but not like as opposed to ירושלים and
שילה, Shilo, it's not like the whole city had a status. So
if you were to bring, let's say a שלמים Shlomin at נוב
Nov or גבעון, Givon, you would not be limited where you could
eat it. You'd bring the קרבן korban and then you could eat
the שלמים anywhere you want, okay, in any city בכל ערי ישראל.
bechol arei Yisrael. All right. So, so
he says you're right, טאקע takeh a problem. If a נזיר, Nazir,
if you bring a נזיר Nazir brings the קרבן or or you
bring a קרבן תודה, korban Toda, you can only eat it in
ירושלים. But here's the explanation about why you can, why it's considered
eat, you can eat it in theory anywhere. Because going back a
thousand years in Jewish history, there was a time when a קרבן
תודה korban Toda or a נזיר Nazir could be eaten anywhere. You'd
bring the קרבן in נוב Nov and גבעון Givon and then you
could eat, you know, the meat or and the, and the bread
anywhere you want. So since there was a time in Jewish history
where it could be eaten anywhere, therefore even nowadays it's also considered
in theory edible anywhere. What, what, well we'll get,
well we'll see, okay. So that seems to be a pretty far-fetched
answer and by the way, as תוספות asks, so why were we
having the problem before about these issues about, you know, whether it
could be eaten anywhere or not? Let's just go back a thousand
years to the time of נוב Nov and גבעון. Givon. So he
tries to deal with that. But anyway, the גמרא seems to have
good reasons to exclude it. It's uses oil, it can't be eaten
out of ירושלים, and it gets around those. Now it had to
get around those because if you focused on those reasons it presumably
wouldn't matter whether you made it to sell in a marketplace or
not to sell in a marketplace, okay,
because then it would be out of, out of, out of the
box, you know, out of, you know, out of the ring. So
we have, so the, the made with oil isn't a problem, it's
only a little proportional oil. The out eaten out of ירושלים isn't
a problem because a thousand years ago it could have been eaten
out of ירושלים, it could have been eaten anywhere. Okay, so we
only have this problem of whether it was watched for the sake
of מצה and or the problem of whether it was intended for
one day or more than one day. So let's take a look.
So the גמרא says like this: תניא ותנא ברייתא. Tanya v'tana braisa.
אמר רבי אילעאי, Amar Rebbi Ilai, שאלתי
את רבי אליעזר, she'alti et Rebbi Eliezer, I asked רבי אליעזר: Rebbi
Eliezer: מהו שיצא בחלות תודה ורקיקי נזיר, mahu she'yeitzei bechallot Toda v'rekikei
Nazir, can you fulfill your obligation with these things? אמר לי, Amar
li, he said to me,
לא שמעתי, lo shamati, you know what? I don't have a tradition
about this. Now that's important because רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer never said
anything he didn't have a tradition about. Okay, so that ended that
discussion. Once he didn't have a tradition, right, there was nothing more
to discuss because he only told me over things he had by
tradition. So I went to a different rabbi. So
באתי ושאלתי לפני רבי יהושע, bati v'shalti lifnei Rebbi Yehoshua, so I
went to ask רבי יהושע. Rebbi Yehoshua. אמר לי, Amar li, so
רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua said: הרי אמרו, harey amru, he actually did
have a tradition about this. חלות תודה ורקיקי נזיר שעשה לעצמו, challot
Toda v'rekikei Nazir she'asa l'atzmo, if you made it for yourself to
use yourself, אין אדם יוצא בהם, ein adam yotzei bahem, you cannot
fulfill your obligation. למכור בשוק, limkor bashuk, if you made it to
sell in the marketplace, יוצא בהם, yotzei bahem, you fulfill your obligation.
Okay, so he had an answer. כשבאתי והרציתי את הדברים לפני רבי
אליעזר, kshebati v'hiratzeti et hadvarim lifnei Rebbi Eliezer, so I went back
and I told רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer, I said hey, רבי יהושע
Rebbi Yehoshua has a tradition about this. So אמר לי, amar li,
ברית, Brit, like it's like an oath, like you know it's a
language of like in truth forsooth or whatever, I mean ברית Brit
literally means covenant, הן הן הדברים שנאמרו למשה מסיני. hen hen hadvarim
shene'emru leMoshe miSinai. That is what was said to משה מסיני. Moshe
miSinai. Now it's again very interesting because you know he needs things
to be of tradition, not figuring it out on your own. He
didn't have this tradition, but maybe somehow it reminded him or somehow
maybe you know it resonated with him and somehow he said, oh,
that must be a genuine tradition of given over to משה מסיני.
Moshe miSinai. And again notice no logic is being used here. It's
all a question: he didn't have the tradition, רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua
did have a tradition, he went back and told רבי אליעזר, Rebbi
Eliezer, רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer sort of embraced it as a genuine
legitimate מסורה. mesora. Okay, now איכא דאמרי, ika de'amri, some say that
he didn't mean this as a positive statement. That his response was
the
following: ברית ברית, Brit Brit,
like by again by oath, הן הן הדברים שנאמרו למשה מסיני hen
hen hadvarim shene'emru leMoshe miSinai ולא טעמא בה, v'lo ta'ama bah, you
know what? Was this a הלכה למשה מסיני? Halacha leMoshe miSinai? You
don't need a reason for this? Like you can just say it
and it's totally arbitrary. Why should it matter if it's made for
yourself or made for somebody else? What type of a teaching is
this? Okay, so he actually questioned the tradition, interesting he questioned it
because it didn't make because it didn't he didn't have. Because it
didn't make sense, right? If it, again, if it was his own
tradition, maybe logic wouldn't have mattered. Right, if it was his own
tradition, it's a tradition. But if it's somebody else's, I'm not going
to accept that. That doesn't make any sense. Okay, so וטעמא מאי,
v'ta'ama mai, so the גמרא says, okay, so let's get to it.
What is the reason it matters who it was made for? So
אמר רבה, Amar Rava, כל לשוק, kol l'shuk, if you make it
for the marketplace, אימלוכי מימלך, imluchi memlach, you have second thoughts and
you say אמרי, amri, you say to yourself, אי מזדבן מזדבן, ei
mizdaban mizdaban, if it sells, it'll sell, ואי לא מזדבן, v'ei lo
mizdaban, and if I can't find any buyers, איפוק ביה אנא, eippuk
beih ana, so פסח is coming up, I'll use it for myself
for מצה. And this by the way proves why we have to
assume it's not sanctified. If it was already sanctified,
you can't change what you're using it for, say forget the קרבן
I'll just eat it for מצה. You can only eat it for
מצה and forget the קרבן if it's not sanctified. It also shows
why the reason can't has to be this question of intent. If
the reason was a more fundamental reason, like it was מצה עשירה
matzah ashirah couldn't be eaten elsewhere, then who cares what your intent
is? At the end of the day, that's a problem. But if
the only problem is your intending it for a קרבן and not
for the מצוה, then we can say as long as in the
back of your mind you realized that you might not be able
to sell it and you might want to use it for the
מצוה, so at some level you were intending to do it for
מצה of מצוה. Or the other idea that it was seven days
versus one day. As long as the whole problem is, oh, you
were only thinking about it as a one-day thing, as long as
in the back of your mind you were realizing you might not
sell it and you might keep it for yourself, so at some
level you were intending for the possibility that it might not just
be for one day, it might be for seven days. And that's
why the גמרא has to skirt all of the other issues and
say the problem is just an intent problem and it hasn't been
sanctified to allow for the idea that when you're doing it to
sell, your intent also has you're holding you have also some intent
to use it for yourself for the מצוה, and that's why it
is good.
Okay, but if you make it for yourself? And but I'm sorry,
but if you made it for yourself and then it is the
problem because...
then it's no good. Right. Why? No, because of the reasons given:
seven days or מצה of מצוה. And as I did say, the
relevant part for us is the possibility that protecting it from חמץ
is not enough to use it for the מצוה, you need intent
for מצה of מצוה. That's not black and white, but that certainly
is a thing that might emerge from one of the positions here
in the גמרא. So we'll continue tomorrow moving from מצה and going
on to מרור. maror. Okay, yes. Alright,
look at that, we ended six minutes early. Yes.